The Nightmare Before Christmas is a fantasy, animation,
family film directed by Henry Selick.
Tired of scaring humans every October 31 with the same old bag of tricks, Jack Skellington, the spindly king of Halloween Town,
kidnaps Santa Claus and plans to deliver shrunken heads and other ghoulish gifts to children on Christmas morning.
But as Christmas approaches, Jack's rag-doll girlfriend,
Sally, tries to foil his misguided plans.
Jack Skellington (singing) / Barrel / Clown with the Tear
away Face (voice), played by Danny Elfman.
Jack Skellington (voice), played by Chris Sarandon.
Sally / Shock (voice), played by Catherine O'Hara.
Dr. Finkelstein (voice), played by William Hickey.
Mayor (voice), played by Glenn Shadix.
Lock (voice), played by Paul Reubens.
The Nightmare Before Christmas (also known as Tim Burton's The Nightmare Before Christmas) is a 1993 American
stop-motion Gothic fantasy film directed by Henry Selick and written by Caroline Thompson.
It tells the tale of Jack Skellington, King of Halloween Town, who stumbles upon
Christmas Town and becomes obsessed with celebrating the holiday himself.
Danny Elfman wrote the songs and score and provided the singing voice of Jack.
The principal voice cast includes Chris Sarandon, Catherine O'Hara, William
Hickey, Ken Page, Paul Reubens, Glenn Shadix and Ed Ivory.
The Nightmare Before Christmas originated from a poem written by Tim Burton in
1982 while he was working as an animator at Walt Disney Productions.
With the critical success of Vincent that same year, Burton began to consider developing the
story as either a short film or a half-hour television special, to no avail.
Over the years, Burton's thoughts regularly returned to the project, and in
1990 he made a development deal with the Walt Disney Studios.
Production, under Burton and Denise Di Novi, started in July 1991.
Disney initially released the film through the Touchstone Pictures label because the studio believed the film's Gothic tone would be "too dark and scary for kids."
The Nightmare
Before Christmas premiered at the New York Film Festival on October 9, 1993, and was given a limited release on October 13, before a wide theatrical release on October 29.
The film was met with critical and commercial success upon
release, and has since garnered a cult following.
It was nominated for the Academy Award for Best Visual
Effects, a first for an animated film.
Thirteen years after its initial release, the film was reissued by Walt Disney
Pictures and was re-released annually from 2006 until 2010.
In 2023, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically or aesthetically significant."
The film explores themes of skeleton, fire, magic, holiday, santa claus.